Miscellaneous Organizations Collection, circa 1824-2011 (ongoing)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Miscellaneous organizations collection
circa 1824-2011 (ongoing)
MS 482
37 boxes (18 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection contains small amounts of primarily printed materials on women's professional, social, political, charitable, and patriotic organizations. Also included are women's rights groups and organizations for consumer advocacy, ethnic and racial equality, community service, civic improvement, social welfare, labor advocacy, war relief, and animal rights. National and local organizations in the U.S. are represented, as well as other countries, especially Canada, England, Germany, India, Japan, and South Africa. Types of materials include articles, pamphlets, periodicals, newsletters, reports, minutes, conference proceedings, brochures, newspaper clippings, histories, memorabilia, and books, plus small amounts of original correspondence, writings, and photographs.
This collection includes small amounts of material by and about women dating from the early 19th century to the present. The myriad of organizations represented include women's professional, social, political, charitable, and patriotic organizations, as well as women's rights groups and organizations for consumer advocacy, ethnic and racial equality, community service, civic improvement, social welfare, labor advocacy, war relief, and animal rights. The collection is arranged in two series: NATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS and INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS. The National Organizations are arranged by country or region, the United States constituting the largest section. Other countries that are prominently represented include Canada, England, Germany, India, Japan, and South Africa. The organizations are primarily national in scope although there are some local organizations documented as well. Types of materials include articles, pamphlets, periodicals, newsletters, reports, minutes, conference proceedings, brochures, leaflets, newspaper clippings, histories, memorabilia, books, fliers, directories, and small amounts of original correspondence, memoranda, unpublished writings, photographs, and six film reels. Some materials are in languages other than English.
U.S. organizations include the American Women's Association, Association for the Advancement of Women, National Consumers League, National Council of Negro Women, Girl Scouts, National Woman's Party, Sigma Delta Epsilon (Graduate Women in Science), and the Women's Educational and Industrial Union. Individuals represented in the collection include Ethel Andrus (American Association of Retired Persons) and Susan Paul Vashon (Missouri Federation of Colored Women). Some of the more obscure organizations found in the collection include the Temporary Asylum for Discharged Female Prisoners (1875); Massachusetts Home for Intemperate Women (1892); and the Women's Patriotic Association for Diminishing The Use of Imported Luxuries (1864).
Some of the organizations that are well-represented under other countries include Black Sash (South Africa), the Young Women's Christian Association (in various countries), Women's Culture Club (Thailand), Lanka Mahila Samiti (Ceylon), Büro fur Frauenfragen (Germany), All Pakistan Women's Association, and the Fawcett Society (England).
SERIES II. INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS includes women's organizations and congresses that are international in scope and purpose. Topics include women's rights, peace, professional women networks, economic development, international law, and international cooperation. Organizations include the Associated Country Women of the World, International Federation of University Women, International Planned Parenthood Federation, and the World YWCA. A large section documents the United Nations' activities relating to women, such as the Commission on the Status of Women, International Women's Year, the Decade for Women, and various reports on the status of women around the world.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
African American women--Societies and clubs--History--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Societies and clubs--History--Sources; Women in charitable work--United States--History--Sources; Women in politics--History--Sources; Women in the labor movement--History--Sources; Women in the professions--History--Sources; Women social reformers--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Women's rights--Congresses--History--Sources; Women's rights--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Societies and clubs--History-Sources; American Women's Association--History--Sources; Associated Country Women of the World--History--Sources; International Federation of University Women--History--Sources; International Planned Parenthood Federation--History--Sources; National Consumers' League--History--Sources; National Council of Negro Women--History--Sources; National Woman's Party--History--Sources; World Young Women's Christian Association--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material on many of these organizations can be found in other collections in the Sophia Smith Collection, especially in subject collections. See especially the Women's Clubs, Temperance, and Countries Collections, and organizations within the Suffrage, Employment, and other subject collections. There are also larger collections of records in the SSC for some of the organizations represented in this collection: Inter-American Commission on Women, International Women's Tribune Center, Zonta, Sorosis, YWCA, and International Congress of Women.
- SERIES I. NATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS
  - Baltic Women's Council: pamphlet, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belgium (Box 1)
    - L'Association Belges des Femmes Chefs d'Entreprises (Box 1)
      - General, 1951-55 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Bulletin Trimestriel, 1952-55 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Conseil National des Femmes Belges, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Canada (Box 1)
    - Canadian Women's Press Club: notes and roster, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lady Aberdeen Library: correspondence, book list and pamphlet, 1960-67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Match International Center: applications and financial statement, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - National Council of Women of Canada/Conseil National des Femmes du Canada (Box 1)
    - General, 1922-28, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Yearbooks, 1961-68 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
      - Proud Heritage: A History of the National Council of Women of Canada by Rosa L. Shaw, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Voice of Women: pamphlets, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Women's Institute: pamphlet and clippings, 1935-61 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ceylon: Lanka Mahila Samiti (Box 2)
    - General, 1947-66, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Annual reports, 1962-64 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - History, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Egypt: Old War Horse Memorial Hospital/Brooke Hospital for Animals, Cairo (Box 2)
    - General, 1955-58, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1957-87 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - For Love of Horses: Diaries of Mrs. Geoffrey Brooke, edited by Glenda Spooner (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - England (Box 2)
    - Animal Defense Society, London: leaflets, 1950-54 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Beauty Without Cruelty, London: pamphlets, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - British Federation of Business and Professional Women: report, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Conference: The Feminine Point of View: report, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fawcett Society, [see box 4] (Box 3)
    - Labour Party: pamphlets, reports, and clippings, 1925-58 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - National Council of Women of Great Britain: pamphlets, handbook, notes, book, journals, and newsletter, 1943-55 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    - National Federation of Women's Institutes, London: handbooks, annual report, "Jubilee Book," and articles, 1923-65 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - National Union of Societies for Equal Citizenship: pamphlets, 1922-29 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - National Union of Women Workers of Great Britain and Ireland: report, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Six Point Group: pamphlet, correspondence, and memo, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Society of Women Writers and Journalists, London: correspondence and reports, 1948-60 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Status of Women Committee: manifesto, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Women's Emancipation Union: report and pamphlet, 1891-92 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Women's Freedom League: pamphlets and flyers, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Women's Liberal Federation: address, speech, and report, 1884-1926 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Women's Local Government Society: pamphlets, 1882-1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Women's Publicity Planning Association: pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Women's Tax Resistance League: pamphlets, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Women's Voluntary Services: pamphlets, correspondence, clippings, and magazine, 1952-67 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - YWCA of Great Britain: historical sketch, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Fawcett Society and Library: accessions lists, articles, annual reports, pamphlets, and correspondence, 1925-78 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - France (Box 4)
    - Association Por L'Emancipation Progressive de la Femme: pamphlet, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - YWCA, Paris: pamphlet, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Germany (Box 5)
    - General and miscellaneous: handbooks and postcard, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Demokratischer Frauenbund Deutschlands: pamphlets and correspondence, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Schwabische Frauenverein: clipping (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Staatsburgerinnen: pamphlets, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Greece (Box 5)
    - Lyceum Club of Greek Women: articles (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - National Council of Greek Women: Christmas card and pamphlet, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hong Kong: Council of Social Service: annual report, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - India (Box 6)
    - Delhi State Council of Women: annual report and minutes, 1957-58 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - National Council of Women in India: reports, 1927-66 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Saroj Nalini Dutt Memorial Association: annual report, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Seva Sadan Societies: annual reports, 1928-56 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Women's Indian Association: reports, 1927-35 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Israel: Women's Organization in Israel: book, pamphlets, and testimony, 1947-49 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Japan (Box 6)
    - College Women's Association of Japan: art book, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Kobe Women's Welfare Association: pamphlets, photographs, clipping, and correspondence, 1922-33 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - List of women's organizations (in Japanese) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Photograph, pamphlets, and ribbon, 1928-36 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Korea (Box 6)
    - Girl Scouts: pamphlets, 1959-63 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - National Council of Women in Korea: pamphlet, report, and newsletters, 1965-67 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - YWCA: pamphlet and book, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous: list of organizations, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Pakistan: All Pakistan Women's Association (Box 6)
    - General, 1957-64 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Seminar on the Role of Women in the Preservation and Development of Cultures in the Community, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Scotland (Box 7)
    - Scottish Unionist Association: program, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Women's Institutes: handbooks, magazines, and craft book, 1937-55 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - South Africa (Box 7)
    - The Black Sash, [see also Periodicals Collection] (Box 7)
      - General: correspondence and pamphlets, 1956-62 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - The Black Sash: The Story of the South African Women's Defense of the Constitution League, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - National Council of Women of South Africa: reports and pamphlet, 1948-63 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - South America: leaflet, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Switzerland (Box 7)
    - Buude Schweitzerischer Frauenvereine: Das neue Zivilgesetzbuch und die Schweizerfrauen, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Zürcher Frauenvereine für Alkoholreie Wirtschaften: books and pamphlets, 1944-54 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Thailand: Women's Culture Club: pamphlets and yearbooks, 1954-57 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Trinidad and Tobago: newsletters, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Turkey: Women's Library and Information Center, Istanbul: calendar, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - United States (Box 8)
    - General: pamphlets and clippings, 1929-78 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority: pamphlets, 1938-69 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - American Association of Retired Persons (Ethel Andrus): pamphlets, correspondence, program, articles, and magazine, 1964-68 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - American Association of Women Ministers: flyer, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - American Purity Alliance: annual report, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - American Women's Association Award: programs, notebooks, and correspondence, 1931-64 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - American Women's Association: pamphlets, correspondence, and newsletters, 1959-65 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - American Women's Council, Washington D.C.: leaflets and correspondence, 1953-54 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - American Women's Voluntary Services: clippings and magazines, 1942-77 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Anti-vivisection: letters, clippings, pamphlets, and articles, 1919-61 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Association for the Advancement of Women, [see box 10] (Box 9)
    - Association for Feminist Consultants: annual reports, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Association for the Relief of Aged Indigent Females: directory of members, 1951-62 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - The Big Sisters: annual reports, 1917-20 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Binding Ties; periodical of the Black Women's Community Development Foundation: newsletter, 1974-75 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Boston City Federation: yearbook, 1927-28 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Boston Conference on Illegitimacy: description of organization, 1920-27 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Boston Student Union: constitution of organization, 1935-78 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Bristol Female Charitable Society: photographs, correspondence, and pamphlet, 1824-75 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Committee on Women in World Affairs: report, 1945-46 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Association for the Advancement of Women: constitution, papers, correspondence, and reports, 1875-93 (Box 10, Folder 1-12)
    - Consumers League (state organizations): reports, pamphlets, and articles, 1900-50 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Country Women's Council: reports, correspondence, folders, pamphlet, and newsletter, 1950-60 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Daughters of the American Constitution, Inc.: pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution: notebook, pamphlet, and articles, 1890-1977 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Defenders of Wildlife, Washington D.C.: pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Delphian Society (U.S.): pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Eleanor Association: newsletter, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Federation of Feminine Franco-Americaine: pamphlet, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Federation of Organizations for Professional Women: newsletters, minutes, correspondence, and newspapers, 1973-80 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Ferne Animal Sanctuary, Shaftesbury, Dorset: pamphlets and book, 1951-59 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Friends' Association for Aid and Elevation of the Freedmen, Philadelphia: mailing, 1865 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Friendship Dinner (composed of cooperating women's organizations in N.Y. area, organized 1927): pamphlets, programs and drafts, 1933-46 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Girl Scouts of America (Box 11)
      - Memo and photograph, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Girl Scout Handbook, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Girls' Club of America: press releases, pamphlets and newsletters, 1978-84 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Girls' Service League: annual report and correspondence, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Hadassah, The Women's Zionist Organization of America: clippings and pamphlet, 1927-71 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Humane education (various organizations): pamphlets, clippings, book, press releases, correspondence, and annual reports, 1897-1964 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Humane Society of the U.S.: pamphlets, bulletins, correspondence, and articles, 1960-65 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Institute for the Study of Women in Transition: pamphlets, data sheets, correspondence, memo, and informational packet, 1976-77 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Inwood House: book, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Juliette Derricotte Memorial Foundation: correspondence, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Ladies' Aid Society of Philadelphia: "letters and copious extracts of letters," 1862-65 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Ladies' Art Association: program, 1877 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Ladie' Association: annual report, 1833 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Ladies' Auxiliary of the Grand Army of the Republic, Asbury Park, N.J.: photograph, circa early 1900s, [see Oversize Materials] (Box 13)
    - Ladies' Auxiliary to the Veterans of Foreign Wars: pamphlets, 1972-73 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society to the Church of Christ in Phillips Academy: pamphlet, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Ladies' Union Relief Association, NY: program, 1865 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - League for the Civic Education of Women: pamphlet, 1912-13 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Loyal Women of the Republic: book of speeches, 1863 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Lucy Stone League, Inc.: correspondence, and pamphlets, 1863-1965 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Magna Charta Dames: pamphlets, 1948-54 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Margaret Brent Fellowship: correspondence, order forms, and newsletters, 1964-68 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Massachusetts Association of Women Workers program, 1903 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Massachusetts Civil Service Reform Association: historical sketch, annual reports, and exhibition pamphlet, 1882-1907 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Massachusetts Home for Intemperate Women: pamphlets, 1892 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Missouri Federation of Colored Women (Susan Paul Vashon): photographs and biographies, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Moral Education Association: photographs, pamphlets, clippings, and program, 1884-1926 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Mount Vernon Ladies' Association: pamphlets and clippings, 1911-66 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People: clippings, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - National Association of College Women: pamphlet, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - National Association of Colored Girls: 1946 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - National Association of Colored Women: pamphlets and articles, 1941-52 (Box 14)
    - National Association of Colored Women's Clubs: clippings, petition, and program, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - National Association of Commissions for Women: handbook, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - National Association of Pro America: newsletters, 1950-53 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - National Association of Women Artists: pamphlets, 1944-48 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - National Civic Federation, Women's Department: brochure, 1912 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - National Congress of Mothers (Box 14)
      - National Congress of Mothers Magazine, 1906 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Proceedings, pamphlets, newsletters, memos, correspondence, and pamphlet, 1897 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - National Consumers League: publications and correspondence (Box 14)
      - General and correspondence, 1933-59 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Child labor, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Labor legislation, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Minimum wage, 1919 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Women workers, 1930-33 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - National Council for Research on Women: memo and clipping, 1953-85 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - National Council for the Woman Citizen: packets, 1924-29 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - National Council of Jewish Women: book, pamphlets, newsletters, annual reports, and photograph, 1943-late 1970s (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - National Council of Negro Women (Box 14)
      - General, 1946-81, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
      - Interracial Conference on Women, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Telefact (newsletter), 1948-57 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Women United, 16th Anniversary souvenir yearbook, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - National Council of Women of the United States: International Directory of Women's Organizations, 1963, [see also Oversize materials] (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs (Box 15)
      - General, 1935-40 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Business and Professional Women's Foundation: newspaper, pamphlets, drafts, news releases, and annual report, 1956-82 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
    - National Humane Education Society: correspondence, pamphlets, newspaper, articles, books, and calendars, 1954-96 (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
    - National League for Woman's Service: military census, pamphlet, and registration forms, 1917 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - National Negro Labor Council: "Resolution on Negro Women," 1952 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - National Woman's Party (Box 16)
      - General, 1916-79, undated (Box 16, Folder 3-5)
      - Alva Belmont House, 1941-51 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Discrimination laws, 1922-43 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - The Story of the Woman's Party by Inez Haynes Irwin, 1921; Up Hill With Banners Flying: The Story of the Woman's Party by Inez Haynes Irwin, 1964 edition (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - National Women's Political Caucus: correspondence, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - National Women's Program Development, Inc.: newsletter, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Needlework Guild of America, Inc.: pamphlets, reports, and fact sheet, 1959-60 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - New England Woman's Press Association: book, 1935 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - New York Asylum for Lying-In Women: annual report, 1827 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - New York Branch Freedman's Union Commission: pamphlet and article, 1862-66 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - New York Female Moral Society: "an appeal," 1836 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Newburyport Society for the Relief of Aged Females: brief history, 1884 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Other Americans, Inc. (M. Murray organizer): clippings, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Philanthropic Educational Organization: clipping, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Pioneer Women: clipping, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Planned Parenthood League of Connecticut: pamphlet, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Professional Women's Caucus: correspondence and meeting notice, 1970-71 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Republican Women of Massachusetts: article, 1872 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Service Bureau of Women's Organizations: directories, pamphlets, and programs, 1945-55 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Sons and Daughters of Democracy: constitution, 1920 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Sigma Delta Epsilon, Alpha Chapter: correspondence, roster, meeting notes, newsletters, constitution, articles, speeches, programs, pamphlets, and initiation song, 1941-79 (Box 17, Folder 15-18)
    - Social Science Club of Newton (Massachusetts): From Hearth to Horizons: 125 Years of the Social Science Club of Newton edited by Kate Stout, 2011 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Temporary Asylum for Discharged Females Prisoners, Dedham, MA: annual report, 1875 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Sanitary Commission (Box 17)
      - General, 1864 (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - Women's Central Association of Relief, 1861-64 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Voice of the Voiceless: pamphlet, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 1)